Okay, so in this video, we are going to
discuss the critical path.
We're actually going to calculate the
critical path.
So in the previous
video, we talked about the
five steps involved in
the critical path method.
So here we're going to go through steps
number one and step number two,
where we're actually going to calculate
the critical path, and then also note that
float on critical path is going to be
zero.
Okay, so here is a typical type of network
diagram, a typical type of network diagram
that you could get on the exam,
right?
So we have nine activities here,
So we have activity A, B, C, D,
E, F all the way up to I.
These are all the different activities
that we've identified.
And we also sequenced these activities,
right?
We figured out the sequence of the
activities.
So we figured out that A is a starting
activity, I is the ending activity.
B, D and G can be
running parallel, and all
three of these are
dependent on A completing.
E is dependent on only D
completing, whereas F is
dependent on B and E
completing and so on and so forth.
So we put them in the proper order,
we sequence them.
And then also, we figured out the duration
for each activity, right?
How long is each activity going to take?
So figure out that A is going to take two
days, B is going to take four days,
E is going to take two days, C is seven
days, et cetera, so on and so forth.
Now, these could be any units of measure.
Although I just mentioned A is
going to take two days and B is
going to take four days, there
could be any units of measure.
There could be weeks, months, hours.
I like to talk to them as though they are
days simply because
it's easy to understand.
But like I said, there could be any units
of measure.
So let's just stick to days in my
explanation.
Now, whenever you see these boxes here,
right, this is a general convention.
The numbers that you see, this is how the
numbers are laid out.
Now, there are a couple of other
conventions as well, but this is the most
common convention, and this is the one
that's actually shown in PINBOC as well.
So on the top left,
number on the top left,
right, top left corner,
that is the early start.
ES means early start.
On the top right, the number there will be
the early finish.
Bottom left is a late start, bottom right,
right, now, whichever convention is used,
like I said, there's a few different
conventions, but whatever convention is
used, generally the
early start, early finish,
late start, late finish
are always reserved.
They're always shown in those corners.
You have the starts on the left and side,
the finishes on the right side.
It's usually down the middle.
middle that those numbers can be slightly
different depending on the convention.
So the one that PINBock uses and the most
common one is this one here.
So on the top, right in the middle,
that number is there is a duration,
which is why you have
the durations here, which is
why you're seeing the
durations right at the center.
At the top, right in the center of the box
is the name of the activity.
Again, that's why we see the name of the
activity, H-F, E, right,
these are inside the box.
and then right down at
the bottom in between
the late start and
late finish is the float.
So that's a general convention that's
used.
Now, step number one then.
My step number one is to figure out the
critical path.
So in order to figure
out the critical path, we
first need to know what
are all the different paths.
And then what are all the duration for
each path?
So what are all the different paths here?
Well, A is the starting activity,
I is the ending activity.
We've got all these other activities in
between.
Every one of these activities need to be
performed.
They're not optional.
We have to perform all of them.
We just have to figure out, well, which
of these is the longest activities, right?
Which of these is the longest path in
order to figure out the critical path?
So, first, we have to figure out what are
all the different paths.
So A is the starting activity.
I is the ending activity.
Basically follow the path.
You know, what are all the paths we can
get from A to I?
So we just follow all of the paths.
So one path then is A, B, C, I.
That's one way of getting from A to I,
just following the paths, right?
Another path is A, B, F, I.
That is another path, right?
A, B, F, I mean, literally, you're just
following the paths here.
Another path then is A-D-E-F-I.
That's another path, A-D-E-F-I.
right and then you've got another path
A-D-E-H-I and then another A-G-H-I.
Alright, so these are all the different
paths, all the different ways we can get
from A-2-I, A-B-C-I, A-B-C-I, A-B-F-I,
A-D-E-H-I, and then A-G-H-I.
So all the different ways we can get from
A-to-I.
So we figured out all
the paths, now we need to
figure out which of these
is the longest path, right?
So we need to figure out the duration.
right and basically just add up all the
durations in the exam they will always
always give you these durations right so
we need to compute these durations and
basically just sum them all up for each
path right so for a b c i then it's going
to be two plus four plus seven plus three
those are the those are the paths two plus
four plus seven plus three that gives us a
total duration of 16 days for ab f i if
you look right a is 2, B is 4,
F is 6, I is 3.
So it's going to be 2 plus 4 plus 6 plus
3, gives a total duration of 15 days.
And then you do the same way as with ADEFI
and ADEHI, right?
So ADEFI then is 2 plus 5 plus 2 plus 2
plus 6 plus 3, total duration of 18,
right?
ADEHI, right, 2 plus 5 plus 2, right,
plus 7 plus 3 gives total duration of 18.
19, and then AG, H.I.
2 plus 6 plus 7 plus 3, total duration of
18 days.
So the question is then, which of these is
the critical path?
Well, remember, the critical path is the
longest path through the network.
So which of these is the longest path?
A.D.E.H.I.
That is the longest path, and therefore,
that is the critical path.
So the critical path then is A-D-E-H-I,
with a total duration of 19 days.
Now, what does that mean?
Right?
What does it actually mean?
Well, in order to
complete this entire project,
it's going to take us 19 days to complete.
We can't complete it any earlier than 19
days.
Otherwise, other activities are not going
to complete.
Now, we have to complete every one of
these activities.
We have to follow every one of these
paths.
But in order to completely finish every
single activity, it's going to take.
take us 19 days.
So 19 days is the critical path.
And typically then we
draw either a double line or
a bolded line showing
that that is a critical path.
So A-D-E-H-I is the critical path.
Now the entire project is going to take 19
days and the whole principle behind a
critical path remember is
any activity that is on the
critical path, there's no
slack, no cushion, zero float.
And float, remember, is shown down here at
the bottom, in the middle.
So float then on critical path is going to
be zero.
So A has a zero float, D has a zero float.
E has a zero float.
H has a zero float, and so does I.
So what does that mean?
That means that if either, if A,
D, E, H or I are delayed in any way,
that's going to be delay on the entire
part.
project.
So in other words, as a project manager,
our focus is on these activities,
making sure these activities don't get
delayed.
What activities can be delayed,
anything not on the critical path.
B, C and G are not on the critical path,
so they can be delayed.
And how long can they be delayed by?
Well, that's why we go through the other
three steps.
Right, the other three steps are then
going to calculate how long B,
C and G are going to be delayed or can be
delayed.
And how long they can be delayed,
remember, is float.
AD, E, H and I are on the critical path.
For a total duration of 19 days,
that is a critical path.
Any of those activities, AD, E,
H, or I are delayed.
They have zero float, therefore that'll be
a delay on the entire project.